<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Building the ELTeC : a progress report</title>
    <author>Lou Burnard for WG1</author>
   </titleStmt>

   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Discussion draft</p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>Born digital</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>

  <revisionDesc>
   <listChange>
    <change><date>2021-02-01</date>Start adding comments from Dymtro; reformat
     for legibility</change>
    <change><date>2021-01-08T12:25:21Z</date>Tidy up header</change>
   </listChange>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>

  <body>
   <div xml:id="SECTION_1001">
    <head>Introduction</head>
    <p>Four years into a five-year COST Action seems a good point to attempt a
     little retrospective evaluation. By this stage in the Action’s history,
     contributors had made good progress towards the stated goal of creating a
     unique European Literary Text Collection, following specific design and
     selection criteria agreed upon by a broad community of European
     researchers. By this time also, a reasonably stable method of evaluating
     the balance of a given collection with respect to those design criteria had
     been developed and agreed upon (see further <ref
     target="https://github.com/distantreading/WG1/wiki/E5C-discussion-paper"
     >https://github.com/distantreading/WG1/wiki/E5C-discussion-paper</ref>).
     The first major Zenodo release (1.0) for the whole ELTeC was also in active
     preparation, and took place in January 2021.</p>
    <!-- For ‘Intro’ section:
“Distant readers” usually, almost always, work with big text corpora, representing entire periods in the history of literature(s). Moretti stressed the need for a new method for studying not individual texts, but “world literary system” of inter-related literatures.[1] The title of the research project, which will be further discussed, also refers to the supra-national construct, “European literary history.” But upon closer examination, it becomes obvious that it rather considers particular European literatures and relations between them. The COST-action “Distant Reading for European literary history” chaired by Christof Schöch and Maciej Eder brought together research teams from 35 countries with a total of more than 100 participants. What main tasks were assigned to the project? As its site informs they include the following:
«1. build a multilingual European Literary Text Collection (ELTeC), ultimately containing around 2,500 full-text novels in at least 10 different languages, permitting to test methods and compare results across national traditions;
2. establish and share best practices and develop innovative computational methods of text analysis adapted to Europe’s multilingual literary traditions;
3. consider the consequences of such resources and methods for rethinking fundamental concepts in literary theory and history».[2]
Thus, the goals of the project are in line with Moretti’s ideas about changing the paradigm of our understanding the literary history.[3] It also responses to those critics of distant reading who underlined the anglo-centricity of this approach as introduced by Moretti.[4] Distant Reading action emphasizes the drive to support inclusiveness, including the language one.
The creation of a multilingual European Literary Text Collection (ELTeC) lies at the core of the project. It involves the preparation of subcollections of national literatures. Preparation here means a set of duties that varies for different national teams.-->
    <p>As of December 2020, 15 of the ELTeC’s 18 individual language collections
     had already exceeded the goal of 50 texts and achieved a conformance scores
     of over 70, while 12 of them had 75 or more texts and a score in excess of
     75. A certain amount of self-congratulation might reasonably be in order.
     However, the leaders of Work Group 1 wished to go beyond that by
     facilitating a broader discussion around the accumulated experience of all
     the collection builders, not simply the “successful” ones. Such a
     discussion might seek to explain why in some cases the stated design
     criteria could not be achieved, possibly leading to a reappraisal of the
     assumptions about a common European literary culture underlying the whole
     project. Discussion of the practical lessons learned in this first phase
     would also, obviously, facilitate further development of the ELTeC and
     similarly constructed corpora.</p>
    <p>Late 2020 was not a very propitious time in which to organise an
     international discussion meeting. However, although the ability to meet and
     discuss research priorities and methodologies informally over shared meals
     and at social gatherings was no longer available to us, we could take
     advantage of distanced conference facilities to review progress
     collectively, using a semi formal virtual meeting format in which each
     participant presented their experience according to a predefined template,
     addressing the following questions:</p>
    <list>
     <item>How was the project organized?</item>
     <item>What is the current state of the collection ?</item>
     <item>How were texts selected? </item>
     <item>How did you learn TEI ?</item>
     <item>How were the texts processed?</item>
     <item>What problems did you encounter?</item>
     <item>What future plans do you have for the collection</item>
    </list>
    <p>The present document attempts to summarize responses to these questions
     provided by participants in the online event on December 8<hi
     rend="superscript">th</hi> 2020. Many thanks are due to all the
     participants. We list here those who reported at the online discussion: </p>
    <p>Michal Kren (CZE), Fotis Jannidis (DEU), Lou Burnard (ENG), Christof
     Schoech (FRA), Anna-Maria Sichani (GRE), Gabor Palko (HUN), Vincas Grigas
     (LIT), Michael Preminger (NOR), Joanna Byszuk(POL), Diana Santos (POR),
     Iona Lionte (ROM), Tomaz Erjavec (SLV), Borja Navarro Colorado (SPA),
     Cvetana Krstev (SRP), Dmytro Yesypenko (UKR). </p>
    <p>The author is responsible – and apologizes in advance – for any
     inadvertently introduced misrepresentation of their reports. The original
     slides are also available in the WG1 repository at <ref
     target="https://github.com/distantreading/WG1/tree/master/zoomParty/slides"
     >https://github.com/distantreading/WG1/tree/master/zoomParty/slides</ref> </p>
    <!-- suggested additional topics -->
    <!-- from Diana:
describe some of the studies that have already been done
with the collection (like NER, direct speech, titles, locations), as well
as studies one would like to do. Maybe also describe some metadata issues
such as measuring (or failing to do so) the reprint copy
Plus, a lot of figures (I mean drawings) such as histograms of size per
language, and/or a mosaicplot for the whole collection (and not only per
collection) and a timeline for the full collection could be nice to have.
-->
   </div>
   <div xml:id="SECTION_1002">
    <head>Organizational issues</head>
    <p>As with other COST actions, funding for the creation of new resources
     such as the ELTeC is not provided by the Action itself. Consequently each
     ELTeC corpus is the result of unpaid or subsidised work carried out by many
     different people, usually on a purely voluntary basis. In some cases (CZE,
     GRE, SLV, SWE, ROM) the work was carried out in close collaboration with
     nationally funded agencies, such as libraries or Institutes of Linguistics
     whose staff managed the project or supplied "volunteer" labour in the form
     of student helpers or technical advice. In others (DEU, FRA, LIT, NOR, POL,
     POR, UKR), management of the project was undertaken by senior researchers,
     usually though not always (ENG) with university affiliations. In some cases
     (HUN, ROM, SPA, SRP for example) the work was framed within the context of
     a masters degree in digital humanities, but in most cases the project was
     managed "for love" by a small group of enthusiasts, in many cases a single
     person, co-ordinating and organizing work carried out by a larger group of
     collaborators, in the context of the Action’s Work Group 1. For further
     details of the many agencies and individuals involved in realising each
     project, please refer to the individual presentations cited above, and to
     the list of collaborators on the project website
     (https://www.distant-reading.net/wg-1/). </p>
   </div>
   <div xml:id="SECTION_1003">
    <head>Current state</head>
    <p>At the time of the conference, ten repositories (DEU, ENG, FRA, HUN, POL,
     POR, ROM, SLV, SPA and SRP) were already able to report conformance scores
     of 70 or above. The web page http://distantreading.github.io/ELTeC/ shows
     the current state of affairs in more detail for all current language
     collections. Of those with lower scores, NOR and UKR were actively engaged
     in building up their holdings after a late start but were optimistic that
     this would be achieved by the time of the next release. CZE, GRE, and LIT
     all reported difficulties in finding enough titles with the right
     characteristics to achieve a balance. In the case of LIT, it is known that
     no suitable titles exist because use of the Lithuanian language was
     forbidden for most of the period covered by ELTeC. In the case of GRE, no
     suitable texts were available in digital form, necessitating a lengthy OCR
     development process. In other cases (for example SLV , SRP or POR) it seems
     that particular categories of novel (usually those with female authors, or
     of a specific length) are disproportionately absent from available
     catalogues or collections. In most cases, it remains a subject for future
     research to determine whether this disparity is a reflection of the actual
     available population or a consequence of collection bias. </p>
    <p>All repositories are encoded to level 1, except for DEU (level 0 only)
     and ENG (which has 12 texts at level 0). So far only SLV has texts encoded
     to level 2. </p>
   </div>
   <div xml:id="SECTION_1004">
    <head>Text selection</head>
    <p>In most -- though not quite all -- cases, ELTeC texts were made by
     repurposing and reprocessing existing digital texts provided by national
     libraries, national language corpora, private or commercial ebook
     collections and similar. For some European languages, the number of
     available pre-existing digital versions is immense, and the problem for our
     corpus constructors was essentially one of selecting appropriate titles
     from a very large list of candidates. Even so, this could be a challenging
     task, since information about author gender, or even whether or not a title
     was considered a novel, is not readily available from traditional library
     catalogue resources. In some cases, for example Romanian and Serbian, this
     preliminary bibliographic effort constituted ground-breaking research in
     itself; other traditions (for example French, English, German) were able to
     benefit from well established bibliographic databases. </p>
    <p>As regards the source from which texts, once identified, were taken, many
     collections followed the two stage approach adopted by the French and
     English collections, first producing a base collection of "low hanging
     fruit" from well-established public domain collections such as Project
     Gutenberg (for English) or Ebooks Libres et Gratuits (for French), and then
     using trial and error to build up a better balanced selection with titles
     taken from other smaller or more focussed collections, with rejected titles
     being transferred to an "extension" collection. By contrast, for German and
     Hungarian, sufficent titles were identified within a single large
     pre-existing language collection (TextGrid for German; MEK for Hungarian),
     but this approach was ineffective in cases such as Lithuanian where even
     the national repository (www.epaveldas.lt) could not provide enough titles
     as previously noted, or in cases where the selected source was less
     complete than expected (such as the Norwegian Bokselskapet portal). </p>
    <p>In most cases, building a balanced collection implied searching across
     multiple sources to locate and process previously identified candidate
     texts. A typical example is the Portuguese collection, which took texts
     from four main sources (www.luso-livros.net 12; www.gutenberg.org 32;
     purl.pt 16; archive.org 31) as well as a further 11 titles from 9 other
     sources, or the Slovenian collection, in which the 65 texts taken from the
     IMP corpus were complemented by a further 29 titles from the Wikisource
     project "Slovene Literary Classics" and by 5 further titles created
     specifically for ELTeC. Similarly, the Spanish collection combines
     resources from the University of Alicante's Miguel de Cervantes Virtual
     Library (52 titles); the Spanish National Library's Hispanic Digital
     Library (8 titles); the University of Wuerzburg's Corpus of Novels of the
     Spanish Silver Age (CoNSSA) project (31 titles) and a few others, including
     the ubiquitous Project Gutenberg. The absence of any single reliable source
     is particularly remarkable for UKR, the most recently launched collection
     which already takes titles from 8 different sources, including private
     initiatives such as Chtyvo (https://chtyvo.org.ua/help/biblioteka/pro-nas)
     or Izbornyk (http://litopys.org.ua/)</p>
    <!--For some literatures there exist big or even large collections of freely available texts formed within the framework of previous research projects and or digitizing activities by national libraries. But for many other literatures obtaining texts for the ELTeC is a serious challenge.
It is obviously much easier to carry out either an individual or collective research if there is a developed collection of relevant literary works at hand. In other words, if those specialized in English or French literatures can drive along the beaten track at high speed straight from the start of their research, then distant readers of most other literatures have to lay these tracks first.
As a rule for each literature we do have a huge number of novels published in periodicals or as separate editions and available on the shelves of libraries. We also have relatively many digitized versions of these publications available on various sites. However, when it comes to novels already recognized and conversed into plain texts and therefore ready for quick and convenient inclusion into the ELTeC-like corpora, their number is rather low.
UKRAINIAN EXAMPLE [For Ukrainian subcollection, private initiatives of making electronic libraries appeared to be surprisingly useful.[5] In some aspects, they not only do not lag behind but are even ahead in comparison with similar collections prepared by national libraries with their big teams involved. It should be also noted that a large number of publications of Ukrainian literature have been digitized in the archives and libraries of North America. Later, many of them appeared on free accessible sites, including those for Ukrainian users.[6]]
It is clear that the compilers of the corpus – in this case, the national subcollections within the ELTeC – have easy access to a big amount of literary texts that can be called “the school collection.” These texts are in active use and their number may be even larger than that required for the ELTeC. But does this mean that one can form a subcollection simply by reformatting this school collection according to the rules of ELTeC? Absolutely not. The texts in the ELTeC subcollections must meet a number of criteria, one of which is the balanced presentation of canonical and non-canonical texts. “School collections” consist of canonical works, and therefore the ELTeC editors should search, scan, recognize, and encode many other, non-canonical texts.
What are the aforementioned ELTeC criteria and what are they for? The collection aims towards representativeness. It does not include a huge number of texts, just 100 novels from each literature first published in the period 1840-1910 with possible extensions.[7] Representativeness is ensured by meeting a number of criteria.[8] The selection of texts takes into account the balance in the presentation of texts written by male and female authors, prose works of different length (“short,” 10-50.000 words, “medium,” 50-100.000 words, and “long,” more than 100.000 words), and equitable inclusion of works published in different years during 1840-1910 pp. As already mentioned, the presence of canonical texts is also limited.[9] Thus, a collected smaller number of texts makes it possible to draw conclusions about a larger array, a broad period in the history of national literatures. With some simplification, one can consider one novel as a ‘representative’ of several others.
The strength of ELTeC is the mentioned inclusion of both the works of the most prominent writers and authors ‘from the second row.’ This way the collection implements Franco Moretti’s thesis of the “great unread.”[10] What is more, ELTeC represents both non-canonical texts within particular European literatures, and ‘non-canonical literatures’ as a whole, those that are virtually absent in the Western critical literary discourse.[11]

-->
   </div>
   <div xml:id="SECTION_1005">
    <head>Taming the TEI tiger</head>
    <p>The ELTeC is a TEI application, if a very simple one, and as such
     requires a degree of technical knowledge, concerning for example usage of a
     schema as well as the basic syntax of XML. Most of the participants had
     prior knowledge of TEI, in some cases dating back a long time (ENG, DEU,
     FRA, SRP). Others had gained awareness from a specific ELTeC training
     session or a general DH introductory course. Those who had had to start
     from scratch (e.g. LIT, GRE) did not report any major problems in finding
     introductory materials on the web. Some specific sources of information
     cited include : </p>
    <list type="unordered">
     <item><ref target="https://distantreading.github.io/Training/Budapest/"
      >ELTeC Training Schools</ref> in Budapest and Wuerzburg (FRA, POL, ROM,
      UKR)</item>
     <item><ref target="https://teach.dariah.eu/course/view.php?id=40">DARIAH
      training materials</ref> (HUN, SLV)</item>
     <item><ref target="https://teibyexample.org">TEI By Example</ref> (UKR)
     </item>
    </list>
    <p>The need for language-specific training materials for students was noted.
     Some participants (HUN, ROM, SLV) had made their own translations or cheat
     sheets for this purpose. </p>
    <!--The texts in the ELTeC collection are linguistically annotated and TEI-encoded.[12] A feature and great advantage of the project is that this conversion and markup are made by native speakers who are usually experts in a specific language, literary and cultural context. They can efficiently and quickly resolve tricky issues for instance those related to historical realia or special linguistic features.
-->
   </div>
   <div>
    <head xml:id="SECTION_1006">Text processing</head>
    <p>Participants used a variety of approaches to the processing of source
     texts into ELTeC-XML, and quite a few different tools. There was broad
     agreement on the steps needed, with some variation around the extent to
     which conversions were automated, depending partly on whether the texts
     processed started life as plain text output from OCR or as marked up texts
     of some kind. Some projects (e.g. DEU, ENG, FRA, SLV) produced workflows in
     which specially written scripts in languages such as XSLT, Python, or perl
     did most of the heavy lifting of converting or inserting markup. This
     worked best where the source material was consistently encoded in a rich
     format that could be mapped readily to the requirements of ELTeC-XML, and
     where large numbers of texts were available in that format. In almost all
     cases, however, some degree of manual intervention was necessary to add
     (for example) minimal structural tagging, as well as to complete the TEI
     Header. </p>
    <p>Conversion and scripting tools specifically mentioned by at least one
     participant : ABBYY Fine Reader (5), atom (3), Beautiful Soup, Calibre,
     docxtotei, jedit, jing, Notepad++ (2), oxGarage, oXygen (7), Pandoc, Perl
     (2), Python (3), Sublime Text Editor, TXM, Unitex, XSLT (3), xmllint. </p>
   </div>
   <div xml:id="SECTION_1007">
    <head>Challenges</head>
    <list type="unordered">
     <item>The lack of available texts of the right kind was a major issue for
      many collections. Where digitized collections existed, they frequently
      lacked non-canonical works, or works by women, or from specific time
      periods. In some cases, the quality of digitization was so poor it was
      found easier to start from scratch, by applying OCR to digital facsimiles,
      where these could be found, or even digitizing the original source texts
      again. </item>
     <item>Where digital texts were plentiful, it was sometimes difficult to
      make a principled choice (ENG), to handle variation in encoding practice
      (FRA), or to normalize them consistently (DEU). </item>
     <item>Changes in the ELTeC schema during the lifetime of the project caused
      problems for some collections (HUN, POL) </item>
     <item>The need to work in close collaboration with other researchers, in
      particular with metadata specialists, was not fully appreciated at first
      (NOR, ROM)</item>
     <item>The "learning curve" associated with mastering TEI XML was steeper
      than anticipated for some participants</item>
    </list>
    <!--The universal principles of text selection and the same annotation standard are needed to get comparable corpora for different literatures at the output. Unfortunately, such unification and ‘distancing’ from the particular literature unavoidably lead to losses. (“If we want to understand the system in its entirety, we must accept losing something”[13]). They are characteristic and unique features of the national contexts, for example, their multilingualism. Since only texts written in national languages can be presented in the ELTEC collection, it is obvious that significant and important branches of literatures written in other languages are cutting off.
UKRAINIAN EXAMPLE [For the Ukrainian subcollection, these are primarily texts in Russian, as well as in Polish and German, written not only by the authors of a ‘second rank’ but also by those considered the national classics. The central figure of the Ukrainian literature Taras Shevchenko with his Ukrainian poems and Russian-language novels does not have a chance to be represented in ELTEC]
There is also a restriction regarding the place of publication. This should be only Europe. That means, novels published, for example, in North America, even in the right time period and in the proper national languages, cannot enter the collection.
As the one interested in the issues of textual criticism and scholarly editing, I would also stress the focus on texts from a particular type. Namely, ELTeC prioritizes versions from separate editions over serial publications in periodicals. It is also desirable to have the first edition of a novel.
UKRAINIAN EXAMPLE [I must say that the latter circumstance added much to my workload as a compiler of the Ukrainian collection. (My guess colleagues also paid extra efforts to this). The Ukrainian editorial practice preferred texts from later editions. As a rule, their choice falls in favor of the last lifetime publication containing the author’s final intentions.[14] Therefore, most of free available Ukrainian texts represent exactly such version. That means I have to check them in comparison with those from first editions, making minor and significant changes.]
But it does not seem right to blame the project for this last limitation as this is a more general issue. Katherine Bode aptly noted that both close and distant reading dismiss the fact that literary works are not a single and stable texts.[15] Researchers just like readers and publishers usually want to deal with exactly that single, classical, right, canonical text. Which almost never exists.
Bode also raised another issue or rather two: 1. collections are selections and they depend on the expertise of compilers; 2. funding plays an important role.[16] Indeed, if COST regulations would provide the financial support of the subcollection compilers that could potentially involve more contributors and provide broader collections at the output. (For example, it may contain more Italian novels as well as the Russian subcollection). The sense of expertise in the formation of ELTeC is closely related to the notions of responsibility and quality of the final result. The responsibility of the members of national teams is the greater, the fewer experts in their literature are among other project participants. For instance, English subcollection can be verified by many members from other national teams who possess linguistic competence and know a few/several/many novels. The situation is different when dealing with “non-canonical” literatures, those that are not in a high demand in the Western critical discourse. The contributors are self-controllers while working on relevant subcollections. At the stage of the collections formation, their colleagues cannot check and correct their work. Only after public release and over some time, the community of readers/users might suggest to make certain changes.
-->
   </div>
   <div xml:id="SECTION_1008">
    <head>Future perspectives</head>
    <p>Naturally enough, some collections with low E5C scores (CZE, GRE, NOR)
     reported that they would be prioritizing production of more texts during
     the last year of the Action. In most places, a functioning workflow was now
     well established, with clear procedures and sources of assistance such as
     student helpers. It was also clear that several collections which had
     already reached the required size would soon be further complemented by
     extension corpora going beyond the original specification in size or scope
     (FRA, HUN, SLV, SRP). Somewhat surprisingly only four (HUN, POR, SPA, SRP)
     specifically indicated an intention to add level 2 tagging in the near
     future. </p>
    <p>Some (SPA, POR, UKR) wished to re-visit some ELTeC design decisions
     concerning language and authorial nationality. Certainly it would be
     desirable to see Galician, Basque, or Catalan collections complementing the
     existing Spanish collection, just as it would be good to see Swiss-German
     and Swiss-French collections. The decision to exclude American writers from
     the English corpus, French Canadian writers from the French corpus, or
     Brazilian Portuguese writers from the Portuguese corpus, while consistent,
     problematizes any attempt to assess for example colonial or diaspora
     experiences as reflected in the 19th century novel. During this period also
     the cultural tradition with which an author is associated is not always
     identical to that of the language in which they wrote: Kafka's uniquely
     Czech experience is written in German; Taras Shevchenko's Ukranian roots
     are expressed in Russian. </p>
    <p>A wide ranging final discussion touched on these and several further
     points. Desiderata for future work ranged from simple tasks like improved
     documentation, in particular an overview of available training material, to
     information about available OCR and metadata handling tools. It was noted
     that individual collection editors were best placed to select and evaluate
     available linguistic annotation tools before creating level2 texts. The
     CLARIN Impact Knowledge Centre at <ref
     target="https://www.clarin.eu/news/impact-clarin-k-centre-digitisation-impact-ckc"
     >https://www.clarin.eu/news/impact-clarin-k-centre-digitisation-impact-ckc</ref>
     was cited as a source of useful information and possibly also of funding. A
     need for better co-ordination and co-operation between the separate
     workgroups of the COST action was identified. </p>
    <p>In conclusion, it also seems appropriate to ask why building the ELTeC
     has been such an appealing task for so many contributors across Europe. The
     role of ELTeC as an exemplary project for courses exploring the Digital
     Humanities, as a useful primary source, or as an enabler of traditional
     historical, literary, and linguistic studies were all mentioned. But
     perhaps the most persuasive and simplest answer was from the Serbian team:
     "Why all this work? Because I love novels... and also, this will be a
     unique corpus..." </p>
   </div>
   <!--
What opportunities can such a representative collection as ELTeC provide researchers? In fact, this question does not presume an exhaustive answer. The multitude of possibilities is limited only by the interest and imagination of the scholars. Having such a representative multilingual corpus, it is possible to conduct a wide variety of studies – especially comparative ones – according to the questions and tasks raised. It is even difficult to predict what exactly these questions will be, as well as whether only literary scholars will be interested in ELTeC (hopefully, not only them). This can be, for instance, the comparison of formal categories of texts in various literatures, their volume and structure within parts and chapters; or consideration of the linguistic features inherent in novels in all subcollections (for example, direct speech);[17] or analysis of the geography of publication (what are the main publishing centers in Europe, why some works were published far away from their potential audience, in other countries, outside linguistic areals).
 -->
  </body>
  <back>
   <div type="notes">
    <note> [1] Moretti Conjectures 2013, 45–47. </note>
    <note>[2] This list is not exhaustive. The project also aims to promote
     training and development of early-career investigators, support new joint
     submissions to national and European projects, and ensure gender balance in
     computer sciences and related fields
     https://www.distant-reading.net/about/objectives. </note>
    <note>[3] Moretti Conjectures 2013, 48. </note>
    <note>[4] Arac 2002. </note>
    <note>[5] For instance, e-libraries Chtyvo
     https://chtyvo.org.ua/help/biblioteka/pro-nas or Izbornyk
     http://litopys.org.ua/. An interesting detail is that it is not easy to
     find information about some of the authors who initiated such large-scale
     (and noble by their intention) projects. Such anonymity may be related,
     among other things, to the fact that these publications do not always
     adhere to copyright regulations.</note>
    <note>[6] There is even a special e-library presenting scans of books
     published outside Ukraine called Diasporiana: https://diasporiana.org.ua/. </note>
    <note>[7] Additional novels that go beyond the number of 100 are included in
     the so-called “extended collections.” Although the release of such extended
     collections within ELTeC is not planned in the nearest future (in order not
     to create a disproportion between subcollections), they are easily
     accessible and can be used by all interested for other purposes
     https://github.com/COST-ELTeC. </note>
    <note>[8] https://distantreading.github.io/sampling_proposal.html </note>
    <note>[9] The concept of canonicity is associated with the number of
     (re)publications of works in the last few decades. Which is an obvious
     simplification as the number of publications cannot serve as a fully
     reliable marker of canonicity or even the popularity of a particular work. </note>
    <note>[10] Moretti borrowed the term from Margaret Cohen, but for her it
     meant rather “literary archive,” unread sources for studies of literary
     works (Khadem 2012, 410) </note>
    <note>[11] More on the two interpretation of non-canonicity see: Khadem 2012
     (418). </note>
    <note>[12] Encoding guidelines might be found at:
     https://distantreading.github.io/Schema/eltec-1.html and
     https://distantreading.github.io/Schema/eltec-2.html. </note>
    <note>[13] Moretti Conjectures 2013, 49. </note>
    <note>[14] The principle of editio ultima (the last authorial edition) has
     dominated not only in the scholarly editing of Ukrainian literature, but
     most of the Slavic literatures (Yesypenko 2020, 50, 60). </note>
    <note>[15] Bode 2018, 33. </note>
    <note>[16] Bode 2018, 22. </note>
    <note>[17] Actually, colleagues have already conducted an exciting reseach
     on detecting direct speech based on 9 ELTeC subcollections (Byszuk et al
     2020). </note>
   </div>
   <div type="bibl">
    <bibl>ARAC, Jonathan: Anglo-Globalism? In: New Left Review 16 (July-August)
     2002, p. 35 – 45. </bibl>
    <bibl>BODE, Katherine: Abstraction, Singularity, Textuality: The Equivalence
     of “Close” and “Distant” Reading. In: BODE, Katherine: A World of Fiction:
     Digital Collections and the Future of Literary History. Ann Arbor :
     University of Michigan Press, 2018, p. 16 – 35. </bibl>
    <bibl>BYSZUK, Joanna et al.: Detecting Direct Speech in Multilingual
     Collection of 19th-Century Novels. In: Proceedings of the 1st Workshop on
     Language Technologies for Historical and Ancient Languages Language
     Resources and Evaluation Conference (LREC 2020), Marseille, 11–16 May 2020,
     p. 100 – 104. </bibl>
    <bibl>KHADEM, Amir: Annexing the Unread: A Close Reading of «Distant
     Reading». In: Neohelicon, 39, 2012: 409 – 421. </bibl>
    <bibl>MORETTI, Franco: Conjectures on World Literature. In: MORETTI, Franco:
     Distant Reading. London–New York: Verso, 2013, p. 43 – 62. </bibl>
    <bibl>YESYPENKO, Dmytro: Printed and Digital Wor(l)ds: Retrospectives and
     Perspectives of Scholarly Editing in Slavic Countries. In: Canadian
     Slavonic Papers, vol. 62, 2020, no. 1, p. 45 – 66. </bibl>
   </div>
  </back>
 </text>
</TEI>
